大家好, 在这个视频中, 我们将讨论一些我称之为经济的东西
Hello. In this video we're going to talk about something that I've referred to as the economy
编程语言。
of programming languages.
这个视频背后的想法是在我们进入之前
So the idea behind this video is that before we get into the
关于语言是如何实现或设计的细节, 我想说一些
details of how languages are implemented or designed, I wanted to say something about
语言在现实世界中是如何工作的, 以及为什么使用某些语言, 而其他语言却不是。
how languages work in the real world and why certain languages are used and others are not.
如果你环顾四周, 会有一些明显的问题出现在任何人身上
And if you look around, there's actually a few obvious questions that come up to anybody
谁会想到编程语言超过几分钟, 一个问题是,
who thinks about programming languages for more than a few minutes. One question is,
为什么会有这么多的东西呢？我们有成百上千的编程
why are there so many of these things? We have hundreds, if not thousands, of programming
日常使用的语言, 为什么所有这些东西都需要存在？为什么不存在呢？
languages in everyday use, and why do all these things need to exist? Why wouldn't one
例如, 编程语言就足够了吗？
programming language for example be enough?
一个相关的问题, 但略有不同的是为什么会有新的编程语言？
A related question but slightly different is why are there new programming languages?
既然我们已经有了那么多的编程语言, 那么对新语言的需求是什么呢
That given that we have so many programming languages already, what is the need for new
要创建的是什么？最后, 当我们看到一个好的编程语言时
ones to be created? And finally, how do we know a good programming language when we see
是什么造就了一种好的编程语言, 以及什么导致了糟糕的编程语言？
it? So what makes a good programming language and what makes a bad programming language?
我想用这个视频来讨论这三个问题, 我们会看到, 我
I just want to spend this video talking about these three questions. And as we'll see, I
认为这些问题的答案很大程度上是独立于语言的技术层面的
think the answers to these questions are largely independent of the technical aspects of language
设计和实现, 但它们本身就很有趣。
design and implementation. But very interesting in their own right.
那么让我们从为什么会有这么多的编程语言的问题开始
So let's begin with the question of why there are so many programming languages. And at
对于这个问题, 至少有一个部分的答案是不太难的, 如果你想
least a partial answer to this question is not too hard to come by. If you think for
几分钟后, 你就会意识到编程的应用领域非常独特
a few minutes, you'd realize that the application domains for programming have very distinctive
以及相互冲突的需求, 也就是说, 设计一种语言是非常困难的
and conflicting needs. That is, it's very hard to design one language that would actually
为所有程序员在每种情况下都做任何事情。
do everything in every situation for all programmers.
让我们来看看一些例子, 一个你可能不会想到的领域
And let's just go through some examples. One domain that you might not think about very
很多是科学计算, 这些都是我们做的大计算
much is scientific computing. So these are all the big calculations that are done for
工程应用主要是大型科学和长期运行的实验,
engineering applications primarily but also big science and long running experiments,
模拟实验。
simulation experiments.
这类计算的需求是什么？通常情况下, 你需要很好的浮动
And what are the needs for such computations? Well typically you need very good floating
点支持, 我把它简写成FP, 你需要对数组和操作的支持
point support. I'll abbreviate that as FP. You need good support for arrays and operations
在数组中, 因为大多数科学应用程序中最常见的数据类型更大
on arrays because the most common data type in most scientific applications is larger
浮点数的数组, 然后你还需要并行度。
arrays of floating point numbers. And then you also need parallelism.
今天就足够了
Today to get sufficient
性能, 您必须在这些应用程序中利用并行性。
performance you really have to exploit parallelism in these applications.
并不是每种语言都能很好地支持所有这些东西, 这实际上是
And it's not every language actually supports all of these things well. This is actually
不是你需要的东西的详尽清单, 而是一些需要的独特的东西。
not an exhaustive list of the things you need but a few distinctive things that are needed.
但是有一种语言传统上在支持这些方面做得很好
But one language that has traditionally done a very good job of supporting these things
是Fortran, 而Fortran在科学界仍然大量使用。
is Fortran. And Fortran is still heavily used in the scientific community.
它最初是为科学应用而设计的, 如果你还记得这个名字
It was originally designed for scientific applications. If you recall that the name
意思是公式翻译, 它随着时间的推移而发展, 它看起来不太像
means formula translation. And it has evolved over time. It doesn't really look much like
原始的语言, 但它总是保留着科学的核心支持者
the original language anymore but it's always retain this core constituency in scientific
在这一领域, 计算机技术仍然是领先的语言之一。
computing and remains one of the leading languages in that domain.
现在, 一个完全不同的领域是业务应用程序, 那么你会怎么做呢
Now a completely different kind of a domain is business applications. And so what do you
这里需要吗？这里你需要像持久化这样的东西, 你不想要
need here? Well so here you're going to need things like persistence. You don't want to
失去你的数据, 企业为了获取数据而陷入困境, 他们需要一种方法
lose your data. Businesses go to a lot of trouble to get the data, and they need a way
为了抓住它, 他们希望这是非常可靠的。
to hold onto it, and they want that to be extremely reliable.
你需要好的报告设施, 因为通常你想做点什么
You're going to need good report facilities. Because typically you want to do something
有了这些数据, 所以你需要良好的报告生成机制, 而且你也想要
with the data. So you need good facilities for report generation. And also, you want
为了能够利用数据, 数据实际上在很多现代企业中
to be able to exploit the data. The data's actually in many modern businesses one of
最有价值的资产所以你需要好的设施来询问关于你的问题
the most valuable assets and so you need good facilities for asking questions about your
数据, 我们称它为数据分析。
data. Let's call it data analysis.
再说一遍, 这不是你需要的东西的详尽清单, 但它是有代表性的
And again, this is not an exhaustive list of things that you need, but it is representative
我想说, 可能是最常见的或者最常用的一种语言
I would say. And probably the most common or one of the most common used languages for
这类应用程序是SQL, 数据库查询语言, 所以关系数据库和
this class of applications is SQL, the database query language. So relational databases and
他们的相关编程语言——我应该说, 语言, 但最明显的是SQL——真的
their associated programming language-- languages, I should say, but most notably SQL-- really
在这个应用程序域中占主导地位。
dominate in this application domain.
然后另一个域, 我们再做一个, 是系统编程。
And then another domain, let's do one more, is systems programming.
我指的是嵌入式系统, 控制设备, 操作系统, 诸如此类的东西。
So by this I mean things like embedded systems, things to control devices, operating systems, things like that.
这里的特征是什么呢, 我们需要非常低的资源控制。
And what are the characteristics here? Well, we need very low level control of the resources.
系统编程的全部意义在于在管理资源方面做得很好
The whole point of systems programming is to do a good job of managing resources and
所以我们需要对资源进行细粒度的控制, 通常有一个时间方面,
so we really want fine grained control over the resources. And often there's a time aspect,
所以你可能会有一些时间限制, 所以你需要能够推理出时间。
so you might have some real time constraints. So you need to be able to reason about time.
因为这些实际上是设备它们需要能够在一定范围内做出反应
Because these are actually again devices and they need to be able to react within certain
时间——如果是网络设备或者类似的东西——你需要响应
amount of time - if it's a network device or something like that - you need to be responsive
对于网络, 很多很多例子都是很重要的, 这些都是
to the network. Lots and lots of examples where timing is important. And these are just
两个方面, 我有点, 我的空间不够用了, 我就讲到这里。
two aspects and I'm a little bit - I'm running out of space here so I'll just stop with that.
但这些都代表了系统编程中需要的东西。
But again these are representative of the kinds of things you need in systems programming.
也许今天仍然是最广泛使用的系统编程语言或家庭系统
And probably today still the most widely used systems programming language or family systems
编程语言是C语言, 在某种程度上是C++家族的语言。
of programming languages is the C and to some extent C++ family of languages.
正如你所看到的, 这些不同领域的需求是完全一致的
And as you can see the requirements in these different domains are just completely
不同的是, 在一个领域中重要的是什么是最重要的
different from each other. What's important in one domain or most important in one
域和另一个领域是不一样的, 我想至少可以想象一下
domain is not the same as in another domain. And it's easy I think to imagine at least
要把所有这些整合到一个系统中是很困难的
that it would be difficult to integrate all of these into one system that would do a good
在所有这些事情上都有工作。
job on all of these things.
这就引出了我们的第二个问题：为什么会有新的编程语言？
That brings us to our second question: Why are there new programming languages?
有这么多的语言存在, 为什么我们需要设计一个新的语言？我是
There are so many languages in existence, why would we ever need to design a new one? And I'm
开始回答这个问题的时候首先要观察的是
going to begin the answer to this question with an observation that at first glance has
这和这个问题毫无关系, 让我花点时间来解释一下。
nothing to do with the question at all. So let me just take a moment to explain it.
我认为程序员培训是编程语言的主要成本, 我认为
I claim that programmer training is the dominant cost for a programming language. And I think
这是非常重要的所以要强调这一点很重要, 它是
this is really important so just going to emphasize the bit that's important here. It's
程序员培训, 用语言教育程序员的成本, 所以我们认为
the programmer training. The cost of educating the programmers in the language. So we think
关于一种编程语言有几件事必须发生在这种语言中
about a programming language there are several things that have to happen for that language
要被使用, 必须有人来设计它, 但那真的不是很贵, 那只是
to get used. Somebody has to design it. But that's really not very expensive. That's just
一个或几个人通常需要编译一个编译器, 但这也是
one or very few people typically. Somebody has to build a compiler, but that is also
实际上并不那么昂贵, 大概10到20个人来做一个大型编译器项目
not actually all that expensive. Maybe 10 to 20 people for a really large compiler project
可以构建一个很好的编译器。
can build quite a good compiler.
真正的成本是所有的用户和教育他们, 所以如果你有成千上万的用户
The real cost is in all the users and educating them. So if you have thousands or hundreds
成千上万的语言使用者, 花费的时间和金钱
of thousands or millions of users of the language, the time and money that it takes to teach
所有的语言都是占主导地位的成本, 这里我指的不是实际的
them all the language is really the dominant cost. And here I don't mean just the actual
买课本, 上课, 诸如此类的费用。
dollar expense of buying textbooks and taking classes and things like that.
这也是一个事实, 程序员必须决定让他们学习是值得的
It's also the fact that the programmers have to decide it's worth it for them to learn
这种语言和许多程序员在他们自己的时间里学习, 但这是他们的一种使用
this language and many programmers learn on their own time, but that's a use of their
时间和花费的时间是真正的经济成本, 所以如果你想想
time and the expense of their time is a real economic cost. And so if you think about the
要教一百万名程序员一种语言的时间是多少, 这是
number of hours that it takes to teach a population of a million programmers a language, that's
这是一项非常重要的经济投资。
really quite a significant economic investment.
从这个观察中, 我们可以很容易地做出一些预测, 再说一遍
Now from this observation, we can make a couple of predictions pretty easily. And again, these
如果你相信这是真的, 那么这就是现在的预测。
are just predictions now that follow from this claim. If you believe that it's true.
我把它擦掉, 然后修正它, 第一个预测是广泛使用的语言会很慢
So let me erase it and fix it. So first prediction is that widely used languages will be slow
要改变, 为什么会这样呢？如果我对一种语言进行了改变
to change. And why should that be true? Well, if I make a change to a language of lots of
人们使用, 我必须教育社区里的每个人关于改变, 甚至
people use, I have to educate everybody in that community about the change. And so even
相对较小的语言扩展对语法的小改动, 小的新特性, 甚至
relatively minor language extensions small changes to syntax, small new features, even
只是在编译器的界面上做一些简单的改变, 如果你有很多用户的话
just simple changes in the interface of the compiler, if you have a lot of users it takes
很长一段时间, 教他们所有这些都是相当昂贵的。
a very long time and is quite expensive to teach them all about that.
所以当语言被广泛使用时, 变化的速度, 它们的变化率就会变慢
So as languages become widely used the rate of change, their rate of change will slow
随着时间的推移, 随着时间的推移, 随着时间的推移, 编程的世界越来越多
down. And this predicts over time as the world of programming grows, as we have more more
世界上的程序员, 我们会期待最流行的语言, 也就是
programmers in the world, we would expect the most popular languages, which will have
越来越大的用户群越来越大, 越来越大, 越来越多
larger and larger user bases so larger and larger programmer basis, to become more and
更僵化, 进化得越来越慢, 我认为实际上你在实践中看到的
more ossified. To evolve more and more slowly. And I think actually what you see in practice
这和那个预测是一致的。
is very consistent with that prediction.
在光谱的另一端, 同样的观察结果几乎显示了
Now at the other end of the spectrum, this same observation makes an almost what appears
作为一种矛盾的预测, 这很容易开始, 很容易开始一种新的语言。
to be contradictory prediction, which is that easy to start, it's easy to start a new language.
事实上, 开始一种新语言的成本很低, 为什么呢？
That in fact the cost of starting up a new language is very low. And why is that? Well
因为你从零用户开始所以在开始的时候基本上没有培训成本
because you start with zero users and so there is essentially zero training cost at the beginning
甚至当你只有几个用户的时候他们的成本就会改变
and then even when you have just a few users the cost of teaching them the changes in the
语言不是很高, 所以新的语言可以更快地进化。
language is not very high. And it's so new languages can evolve much more quickly. They
可以更快速地适应变化的情况, 而实验的成本并不高
can adapt much more quickly to changing situations. And it's just not very costly to experiment
用一种新的语言, 这两件事之间有一种张力。
with a new language at all. And there's a tension between these two things.
什么时候程序员会在一种广泛使用的现有语言之间做出选择
When is a programmer going to choose between a widely used existing language that perhaps
不会很快改变, 一种全新的语言, 他们会选择它
doesn't change very quickly, and a brand new language? Well they're going to choose it
如果生产力, 如果他们的生产力超过了培训成本, 那么如果他们察觉到
if the productivity, if their productivity exceeds the training cost. So if they perceive
通过花一点时间和金钱来学习这种新语言, 他们是
that by spending a little bit of time and money to learn this new language, they're
在相对较短的时间内, 他们的生产力将会提高
going to be much more productive over a relatively short period of time then they're going to
换一个开关。
make the switch.
那么什么时候会发生这种情况呢？把这些都放在一起是很有可能的
So when is this likely to happen? Well putting this all together languages are most likely
被用来填补一个空白, 这是一个来自于程序员的预测
to be adopted  to fill a void. And again this is a prediction that follows from the fact that programmer
培训是主要的成本, 这是什么意思呢, 我的意思是, 编程
training is the main cost. What do I mean by this? Well what I mean is that, programming
语言是有目的的, 人们用它们来完成工作, 因为我们还在
languages exist for purpose, people use them to get work done. And because we're still
在信息革命的过程中出现了新的应用领域
in the middle of the information revolution and there are new application domains coming
一直都是这样。
along all the time.
所以每隔几年就会出现一种新的编程方式
So there are new kinds of programming that emerge every few years or even more often
更重要的是, 就最近的历史而言移动应用现在已经成为了
than that. So just in terms of recent history mobile applications are now something that's
相对较新的, 而且有很多新技术正在被建立起来以支持移动计算。
relatively new. And there's a lot of new technology being built up to support mobile computing.
几年前, 互联网本身就是一个新的编程平台和一群人
A few years ago it was the internet itself was a new programming platform and a bunch
在这段时间里, 像Java这样的新编程语言开始了。
of new programming languages like Java in particular got started during that time.
所以一个新的编程领域是开放的因为技术改变了人们的需求
So a new programming niche is open up because the technology changes that what people want
与软件的变化有关, 这为语言创造了新的机会。
to do with software changes. And this creates new opportunities for languages. The old languages
变化很慢, 所以他们很难适应这些新领域。
are slow to change and so they have some difficulty in adapting to fit these new domains. And
他们并不一定很适合他们因为我们讨论过的原因
they aren't really necessarily well suited to them for the reasons we talked about on
之前的幻灯片上有一个问题因为很难有一种语言
the previous slide with the previous question because it's hard to have one language that
包含了所有你想要的功能。
incorporates all the features you would want.
所以这些语言对于这些应用来说不一定是完美的
And so there are so these languages are not necessarily perfect for these application
领域, 他们适应新形势的速度很慢, 这往往会带来新的变化
domains. They're slow to adapt to the new situation. And this tends to call forth new
语言, 所以当有新的机会和应用领域时, 如果有的话
languages. So when there's a new opportunity and some application domain. If there are
足够多的程序员支持这种语言, 通常会出现一种新的语言。
enough programmers to support the language, often a new language will arise.
只是想指出另一个可以从这个观察中得出的预测。
Just want to point out another prediction that can be made from this one observation.
我要强调的是, 程序员培训是每一种编程语言的主要成本。
That programmer training and I'll underline that, is a dominant cost per programming language.
也就是说, 新语言看起来就像旧的语言, 也就是说, 新语言很少会完全
And that is that new languages  tend to look like old languages. That is that new languages are rarely if ever completely
新的, 他们和一些前任的语言有相似之处有时也有一些
new. They have a family resemblance to some predecessor language sometimes a number of
前身语言。
predecessor languages.
为什么呢？部分原因是很难想象真正的新事物, 但我认为
And why is that? Well partly that it's hard to think of truly new things. But also I think
如果这对经济有好处那就是通过减少培训成本来降低培训成本
if there's an economic benefit to this namely that it reduces the training cost by having
你的新语言看起来像一种古老的语言, 通过利用人们已经知道的东西
your new language look like an old language, by leveraging off what people already know
关于旧的语言, 你可以让人们更容易地学习语言
about the old language, you make it easier for people to learn the language and make
他们学得更快, 最经典的例子是Java和C++,
them learn it more quickly. And the most classic example of this is a Java versus C++, where
Java的设计看起来很像C++, 我认为这是非常有意识的
Java was designed to look a lot like C++. And that was I think very conscious to make
所有现有的C++程序员都可以轻松地在Java中开始编程。
it easy for all of the existing C++ programmers to start programming in Java.
最后, 我们可以问自己什么是好的编程语言, 不幸的是
Finally, we can ask ourselves what is a good programming language. And here unfortunately
情况就不那么清楚了, 我只会说没有, 我就会
the situation is much less clear. I would just make one claim that there is no and I'll
强调语言设计没有普遍接受的标准, 我的意思是什么？
emphasize no universally accepted metric for language design. And what I mean by that?
我想这句话最重要的部分是被普遍接受的部分。
Well I guess the most important part of this statement is the universally accepted bit.
所以我的意思是人们不同意什么是好的语言。
So I mean that people don't agree on what makes a good language.
这里有很多度量标准人们提出了很多测量编程的方法
There are lots of metrics out there and people have proposed lots of ways of measuring programming
但是大多数人都不相信这些是很好的衡量标准
languages but most people don't believe that these are very good measures and there is
当然没有共识, 如果你只看程序员的世界, 他们就不会同意
certainly no consensus. If you just look at the world of programmers, they can't agree
关于什么是最好的语言, 并说服你自己, 去看一看
on what the best language is and to convince yourself of this, just go and take a look
在很多新闻集团的帖子里人们会陷入半宗教的争论
at any of the many news group posts where people get into a semi religious arguments
关于为什么一组语言或一种特定的语言比另一种语言更好。
about why one group of languages or particular language is better than another language.
但即使是在科学界的研究团体中也有设计人员
But even in the research community in the scientific community in among people who design
语言, 我想说的是, 对于什么是好的语言, 并没有普遍接受的共识。
languages, I would say there is no universally accepted consensus on what makes a good language.
为了说明试图提出这样一个指标的困难, 让我们来看看
And to just kind of illustrate the difficulties in trying to come up with such a metric, let
我讨论了一个我听过的人严肃地提出的问题这是一件好事
me discuss one that I've heard people propose in all seriousness and that is that a good
语言是人们使用的, 我在这上面加个问号因为我不相信这个
language  is one people use. And let me put a question mark on that because I don't believe this
声明。
statement.
我想这是一个瞬间的反思我可以让你们相信这不是
And I think a moment's reflection with a moment's reflection I can convince you that this isn't
这是一个很好的衡量标准, 从积极的方面来看, 我认为这是一个很好的论证
a great measure. On the positive side I guess the argument for this is that it's a very
很明显, 它衡量的是语言的流行程度, 实际上有多少人
clear measure. It measures the popularity of the language. How many people are actually
在某种意义上, 使用它和可能的语言被更广泛地使用
using it and presumably languages are more widely used for a good reason. In some sense
也许他们是更好的语言, 但这暗示着如果你相信这一点
perhaps they are better languages. But this would imply if you believe this and follow
它的逻辑结论是, Visual Basic是所有其他编程中最好的语言
it its logical conclusion that Visual Basic is the best language above all other programming
语言。
languages.
我并没有反对Visual Basic, 它是一个设计良好的系统但我甚至不认为
And I've nothing against Visual Basic. It's a well designed system but I don't even think
Visual Basic的设计者, 会声称它实际上是世界上最好的编程
the designers of Visual Basic, would claim that it is in fact the world's best programming
语言, 正如我们在讨论中看到的那样, 有很多很多其他的
language. And as we saw in the discussion that we just had, there are many, many other
除了技术上的优秀之外, 还有哪些因素会影响到编程语言
factors besides technical excellence that go into whether a programming languages is
广泛使用或不使用。
widely used or not.
事实上, 技术上的卓越可能不是最重要的原因
And in fact technical excellence is probably not even the most important reason that a
语言可能会被使用, 它更多地涉及到它是否涉及到一个利基或应用
language might be used. It has much more to do with whether it addresses a niche or application
没有更好的工具的领域, 一旦它建立起来并且有很多
domain for which there isn't a better tool. And then once it's established and has lots
当然, 在历史上有惯性帮助生存, 这就是为什么我们
of users of course there's inertia in history that aided in surviving. And that's why we
仍然有Fortran和钴还有很多其他的语言很久很久以前
still have Fortran and Cobalt and lots of other languages from long long ago that we
如果我们从今天开始就能做得更好。
could if we were starting over today designed much better.
因此, 为了结束这段关于编程语言经济的视频, 我认为最重要的是
So to conclude this video on the economy of programming languages, I think the two most
需要记住的重要事情是应用领域的需求是相互冲突的
important things to remember are that application domains have conflicting needs and therefore
要设计一个包含你想要的所有东西的系统是很困难的
it is difficult to design one system that incorporates everything that you would like
所以你不能把你想要的所有特性都放到一个系统中
to have. So you can't get all the features that you would like into a single system in
一个连贯的设计至少是很难做到的所以要花很多时间
a coherent design at least it's very hard to do that and so it takes a lot of time to
向现有系统添加新特性。
add new features to existing systems.
第二点是程序员培训是编程的主要成本
And the second point is that programmer training is the dominant cost for programming
语言, 这两件事, 这两个观察, 解释了为什么
language. And together these two things, these two observations, these really explain why
我们有了新的编程语言, 因为旧的语言很难改变
we get new programming languages, because the old languages are difficult to change
当我们有新的机会时, 设计一个新的机会往往更容易, 也更直接
and when we have new opportunities, it's often easier and more direct to just design a new
这是一种语言, 而不是试图移动整个程序员群体和一个
language for those rather than trying to move the entire community of programmers and an
现有的系统来适应这些新应用程序。
existing systems to accommodate those new applications.